<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, to Mr. Speaker; concerning a randezvouz of the army, for the quieting of all distempers therein, and recovering the antient discipline thereof. With the desires and proposals of the Generall Councell of the Army, for the easing the countrey, and taking off free quarter. By the appointment of the Generall Councell of the army. Signed Wil. Clarke.</title>
            <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84774</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E413_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863982</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161275</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84774)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161275)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 65:E413[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, to Mr. Speaker; concerning a randezvouz of the army, for the quieting of all distempers therein, and recovering the antient discipline thereof. With the desires and proposals of the Generall Councell of the Army, for the easing the countrey, and taking off free quarter. By the appointment of the Generall Councell of the army. Signed Wil. Clarke.</title>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for George Whittington, at the Blew Anchor in Cornhill neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter is signed and dated: Putney 8. Novem. 1647 T. Fairfax.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 11th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Pay, allowances, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161275:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LETTER From His Excellency Sir Thomas Fairfax, TO M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> SPEAKER; CONCERNING A Randezvouz of the Army, for the quieting of all Diſtempers therein, and recovering the Antien<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Diſcipline thereof.</p>
            <p>With the Deſires and Propoſals of the Generall Councell of the Army, for the eaſing the Countrey, and taking off Free Q<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arter.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>BY the Appointment of the Generall Councell of the Army.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Signed WIL. CLARKE.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <add>Nou: 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </add> 
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>George Whittington,</hi> at the Blew Anchor in Cornhill neere the Royall Exchange, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:161275:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:161275:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Letter from His Excellency Sir</hi> Thomas Fairfax, to the Speaker of the Houſe of Commons.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SJR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>BEing very much troubled at the ſad diſtractions of the Kingdome for want of Pay, and ſuch other neceſſary ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction as we have long wayted upon you for, not taking ſo much pleaſure to ſay whence the Cauſe of all this trouble comes, as to uſe my endeavour to give a timely and effectuall remedy to ſo much thereof, as is of neereſt concern<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment to mee. I thought fit to let you know, That by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Generall Councell of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, J have appointed a Randezvouz very ſpeedily, and they have very unanimouſly
<pb facs="tcp:161275:3"/>offered to repaire to their ſeveral charges, and improve to their utmoſt endeavours with the ſeverall Regiments; <hi>for the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>e<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of them and recovering of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Diſcipline of the Army, thereby to render it more ſerviceable to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Kingdome: And to the end, your expectations, and the Deſires of all good men may be anſwered by a good iſſue in this work of ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment to the Kingdome.</hi> J thinke fit by the ſame advice to offer unto you theſe particulars incloſed, beſeeching you, That if more weighty buſineſſes of the Kingdom do not let you would bring them to a ſpeedy determination; That ſo your care of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my may appeare, and my ſelf and the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be thereby inabled to let the Souldiers ſee we take ſuch conſideration of them, as becomes us, and have ingaged our ſelves unto. And J doubt not, but thereby we
<pb facs="tcp:161275:3"/>ſhall be inabled to let you ſee, that this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my wil appear as it hath ever profeſt; to be really ſeeking the good of this Kingdome, and approving it Self faithful in Your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which hath been, and ever ſhal be the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very humble Servant, <hi>T. Fairfax.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Putney <date>8. Novem. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>For the Honourable <hi>Wil. Lenthal</hi> Eſq; Speaker of the Honorable Houſe of Commons.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="proposals">
            <pb facs="tcp:161275:4"/>
            <head>The Propoſals of the Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Army to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
            <p n="1">I. IT is deſired, That ſix Weeks pay (if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hle) if not a Moneths pay preſently ſent down to the Army.</p>
            <p n="2">II That the Arreares may be voted to be paid out of the remainder of Biſhops lands, Deans and Chapters Lands to bee ſold in the ſame manner as the Biſhops Lands, reſerving a competency to thoſe that have a legall intereſt therein, and have not forfeited the ſame by Delinquency, and two thirds out of Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents Compoſitions, who have not yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and out of Forreſt Lands.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:161275:4"/> III. We deſire, that the houſe will be pleaſed ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make proviſion; That when this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths Pay is out, there ſhall be conſtant pay to enable the Souldier to avoid the Oppreſſion of the People by free quarter, then which, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more grievous unto Us: And in caſe they doe ſo, wee ingage our ſelves to make it death for any man to take free quarter, or if the Parl. do find, That the Counties will not ſo readily bring in their Money, we ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, if enabled thereunto, ſo to diſpoſe of the Army, and of the ſeverall Counties, as that the Monies ſhall be raiſed, and the People punctually ſatisfied for their quarter; provided that there may be an increaſe of the ſaid Tax to an hundred thouſand pound a Month, for the payment of this Army, and the other Forces continued in the Kingdome, and thoſe that are to go for Ireland, and the disbanding of thoſe that be ſupernumerary, untill the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall otherwiſe provide, by Exciſe, or otherwiſe, for eaſing the ſaid Taxes.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Laſtly, we declare, That if this courſe bee taken, that as we have engaged, that none ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:161275:5"/>upon paine of death, take any thing from any Inhabitant in this Kingdome againſt his will, wherin we ſhal be punctuall depoſitive, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo we ſhall give aſſurance. That no man ſhall be forced to bee quartered upon againſt his conſent, provided there may be an allowance for lodging, firing, and candle, or the owners upon whoſe houſes quarters are aſſigned, to be had in other places, to be allowed to thoſe that ſhall quarter.</p>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
